☆独家制作☆
喜马拉雅主播 & 微信公众号:
美国青少年英语
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
地球脉动 III
This is the entrance
这里是通往
to one of the greatest of natural wonders.
最伟大自然奇观之一的入口
Hang Son Doong, in Vietnam.
越南韩松洞
It's thought to be the largest cave on Earth.
这里被认为是地球上最大的洞穴
Here, 200 metres underground,
深达200米
for just a few weeks a year,
一年中只有几周时间
sunbeams cast light through a hole in the cave's roof.
阳光能透过洞顶的缝隙 照射入内
There is just enough light
这点阳光刚好
to enable plants to grow.
能满足植物的生长
But travel deeper,
随着继续深入
and darkness returns.
黑暗再次笼罩
And you reach the limit
这里的极端环境下
of where life can exist.
生命如履薄冰
极端环境
These most extreme places on our planet
人类通常难以涉足
are often hard for us to reach.
这些地球上最极端的环境
Indeed, this cave was only recently discovered.
事实上 这个洞穴是最近才被发现的
And it contains many surprises.
其中蕴藏着许多惊喜
Cave pearls.
洞穴珍珠
Once tiny sand grains,
曾经微小的沙粒
now spheres the size of tennis balls.
如今足有网球大小
And giant stalagmites...
巨大的石笋
..formed over centuries
数百年来
by billions of individual drops of water.
由几十亿滴水日积月累而成
Underground rivers have carved
地下河在石灰岩中
this great passage through the limestone.
开辟了这条巨大的水道
Over five miles long
长度超过8公里
and wide enough in places
宽度足以容纳
to accommodate a jumbo jet.
一架大型喷气式飞机
And it is here,
而就在这里
in the cave's furthest chamber,
洞穴的最深处
that life can be found.
孕育着生命
Translucent cave fish...
半透明洞穴鱼
..and shrimps.
洞穴虾
Isolated for millennia,
几千年来与世隔绝
feeding on little more than the nutrients from the jungle above.
仅以头顶丛林里的营养物质为生
The fish are completely blind
洞穴鱼没有视觉
and find their way about by touch alone.
只能依靠触觉辨认方向
These underground worlds are at the very limit
在这些地下世界中
of where life can exist.
生命如履薄冰
But above ground,
而在地面以上
our planet's most extreme conditions
地球上最极端的环境
are found at the poles.
非两极莫属
Here in the north,
在北极
winter temperatures can drop to -50 degrees Celsius.
冬天的气温可以降至零下50度
For four months of the year,
一年中的四个月里
there is barely a glimmer of sunlight.
几乎见不到一缕阳光
But here, too,
但在这里
life finds a way to survive.
生命同样有其生存之道
A pack of Arctic wolves.
一群北极狼
Their dense fur has protected them
浓密的皮毛提供的保护
through months of bitter cold.
帮助它们熬过了数月的严寒
But now the sun is returning.
但如今阳光再次洒落大地
This is Ellesmere Island.
埃尔斯米尔岛
The short summer gives the wolves a chance to rebuild their strength.
短暂的夏季 使狼群得以重新积攒力量
But here in the Arctic...
但在北极这片极端的环境
..life is never easy.
生命举步维艰
This pack is led by an experienced female.
狼群的首领是一只经验丰富的雌性北极狼
If she can't lead them to food,
如果雌狼无法带领狼群找到食物
the coming winter could be their last.
它们将很难撑过即将到来的寒冬
Prey is spread over such a vast area
猎物分散在如此广阔的区域
that they must be constantly on the move...
狼群必须不断移动
..in search of it.
以寻找猎物
But finding prey is only the beginning.
但寻找猎物 仅仅是狩猎的第一步
Musk oxen.
麝牛
They are five times the size of a wolf.
体型是北极狼的五倍
The conflict between wolf and oxen is an ancient one,
北极狼与麝牛之间的明争暗斗由来已久
and has been waged since the Ice Age.
可追溯至冰河时代
Each side knows the other's tactics.
互相对彼此的战术都熟稔于心
The wolves try to isolate
北极狼试图孤立
the weak or the young.
体弱幼小的麝牛
A calf stumbles...
一只小牛跌跌撞撞
..and the pack leader immediately closes in.
狼群首领立即靠近过来
But the herd regroups,
但麝牛群重整旗鼓
horns at the ready.
牛角蓄势待发
Stalemate.
陷入僵局
But it can only be brief.
但只是短暂的僵局
This time, the herd race to higher ground.
麝牛群冲向高地
As they reach the top of the ridge,
当麝牛群抵达山脊顶部时
the males turn to defend themselves.
雄性麝牛转身面向敌人以自卫
Stalemate...
再次
..again.
陷入僵局
Every unsuccessful hunt
狩猎每失败一次
leaves the pack weakened.
狼群便虚弱一分
This could be an easier meal.
唾手可得的午餐
But something is not right.
但有些不对劲
This musk ox has died from a disease.
这头麝牛死于疾病
Outbreaks like this are becoming increasingly common
随着北极地区气候变暖
as the climate warms across the Arctic.
类似的疫情变得越来越普遍
Despite their hunger,
尽管饥肠辘辘
the pack don't eat this carcass.
狼群还是放弃了这具尸体
Another herd.
新的麝牛群
Another chance for the pack.
新的机会
This time, the wolves manage to split the herd.
这一次 北极狼驱散麝牛群
That may improve their chances.
成功率得以提高
The lead female makes sure that the oxen
首领雌狼确保麝牛
do not reach the ridge again.
无法逃往山脊
With one less defender, the calf is more vulnerable.
随着保护的减少 小牛岌岌可危
A much-needed meal.
雪中送炭
The wolves must continue to make the most
北极狼群必须充分利用
of the remaining weeks of summer...
夏季的最后几周
..so when winter returns
从而在这片
..they're ready to endure
地球上最恶劣的生存环境中
some of the harshest conditions
储备能量
that exist on planet Earth.
迎接即将到来的严冬
Such inhospitable extremes
如此不宜居的极端环境
are not only found at the poles.
并非只存在于两极
As altitude increases...
随着海拔上升
..temperatures fall.
气温大幅下降
Here, too, animals must make the most of the seasonal change.
在这里 动物同样必须充分利用季节变化
Particularly if you're ready to mate.
尤其是处于繁殖季节时
A male common frog
法国阿尔卑斯山
in the French Alps.
一只雄性林蛙
He has spent all winter hibernating under the ice.
它整个冬天都在冰下冬眠
But now it's time to wake up.
但现在是时候清醒过来了
Being cold-blooded, he needs the sun to warm his body.
林蛙是变温动物 需要晒太阳来暖和起来
But once it sets in a few hours' time,
但几小时后一旦太阳落山
he could freeze to death.
林蛙便会冻死
So finding a mate is urgent.
因此 寻找伴侣迫在眉睫
The weather is good.
天气不错
And he starts to sledge.
雄林蛙动身了
But this is not a one-frog race.
但竞争对手也没闲着
Dozens are rushing to the breeding pool.
数十只林蛙涌向水塘
This many frogs out on the slopes...
斜坡上爬满了林蛙
..doesn't go unnoticed.
有眼睛正盯着这里
You can't afford any slips.
千万不能滑倒
It was all going so well.
一切都很顺利
Made it.
成功抵达
But all the females have already got partners.
但所有雌林蛙 都已名花有主
There's only one thing for it.
只有一个办法了
Wrestling.
强取豪夺
Not this time.
功亏一篑
Another latecomer.
又一只姗姗来迟的林蛙
A female.
一只雌林蛙
Could she be the one?
真命天女会是它吗
Sometimes being late can pay off.
来得早不如来得巧
After all his efforts, the male is not going to let this chance
煞费苦心的雄林蛙 不会让这个机会
slip through his fingers.
再次从指间溜走
This is the cedar forest of the Atlas Mountains, in North Africa.
这里是非洲北部阿特拉斯山脉的雪松林
These Barbary macaques enjoyed a summer of plenty,
这群地中海猕猴 享受了丰收的夏季
but now they're paying the price.
但好景不常
Winter here can be brutal.
这里的冬季刺骨严寒
In some years, over half the group perish.
某些年 半数以上的猕猴死在了冬季
But in this macaque society,
在这样一个社会
the more social the monkey,
猕猴的社交能力越强
the more likely it is to survive.
生存几率便越大
Keeping warm by huddling can make all the difference.
抱团取暖效果显著
But they can't huddle all day.
但也不能一直抱在一起
They must, eventually, break apart to feed.
它们为了觅食 不得不从温暖中抽身
They spread out, searching for food.
猕猴四散分开 寻找食物
But each night, the group return to huddle in the cedar trees.
但到了晚上 猕猴群便会回到雪松树上挤成一团
No-one wants to be left out.
谁也不想被落下
Especially the infants.
尤其是猕猴幼崽
This baby, somehow, has got separated.
不知怎的 这只猕猴幼崽跟大部队分散了
He must get back to the life-saving warmth of the huddle,
它必须回到温暖的怀抱中 以维系生命
and soon.
而且必须尽快
But there is an obstacle.
然而有一个问题
A grumpy male is giving the baby a rather cold shoulder.
一只脾气暴躁的雄猕猴对猕猴幼崽相当冷淡
Maybe a more subtle approach.
换一种更隐蔽的方式
The male decides to leave.
雄猕猴决定离开
At last...
终于
..an enthusiastic reception.
得到了热情的欢迎
The male has had less luck.
雄弥猴则运气不佳
It could be a long night.
将是漫漫长夜等着它
Huddling might seem a simple expression of affection,
抱团似乎是一种表达情感的简单方式
but among these macaques it's essential for survival.
但对于这些地中海猕猴来说 这对于生存至关重要
And not just here.
而这样的行为并非绝无仅有
5,000 miles away, in the forests of Mexico,
8000公里外的墨西哥树林中
monarch butterflies, in millions,
数百万只黑脉金斑蝶
also huddle for survival.
也为了生存挤作一团
All of them have travelled across North America
它们集体飞越北美大陆
to escape the winter that is coming there.
躲避冬季的严寒
This forest, at an altitude of 3,000 metres,
这片海拔3000米的森林
might seem to offer little comfort...
似乎并不能提供舒适的环境
..for temperatures here can drop below freezing,
因为这里的气温可降至零度以下
and that could kill the butterflies.
如此低温能置蝴蝶于死地
But in fact, a thin layer of warm air
然而事实上 树冠保有
trapped by the tree canopy protects them,
薄薄的一层暖空气保护着蝴蝶
and will do so throughout the winter...
只要森林不受干扰
..provided that the forest remains undisturbed.
就能一整个冬天为蝴蝶提供保护
Unpredictable extremes of weather, however,
然而 不可预测的极端天气
can disrupt this delicate balance.
会破坏这一微妙平衡
Strong winds can push deep into the forest, chilling the air.
强风吹进森林深处 降低气温
Hundreds of thousands of butterflies
数十万只蝴蝶
may be blown from the branches.
受强风席卷 掉下树枝
In some years, storms kill 75% of hibernating monarchs.
某些年 75%冬眠中的黑脉金斑蝶死于风暴
This one has survived...
这只蝴蝶得以幸存
..but on the ground.
但也掉落在地
And night-time frosts are fatal.
夜间的霜冻足以致命
It can't stay here and live.
因此它不能留在这里
It is too cold to fly,
尽管天气过冷 无法飞翔
but it must get back into the tree branches somehow.
但它必须找个办法 回到树枝上
So it starts to climb.
因此它开始爬树
It's the equivalent of a human climbing up a skyscraper.
困难程度相当于 人类徒手爬上摩天大楼
Safety, at last.
终于安全了
As spring returns,
春天来临时
the monarchs wake from their long slumber.
黑脉金斑蝶从漫长的沉睡中苏醒
And now starts one of the Earth's greatest natural spectacles.
地球上最伟大的自然奇观之一 就此拉开帷幕
But this mass awakening is under threat.
然而 这种集体复苏的生活习性正面临威胁
The changing climate is creating more extreme weather,
气候变化引发越来越多极端天气
and storms are becoming more frequent.
风暴也越来越频繁
But, for now, this miracle of nature continues.
但就目前而言 这一自然奇迹仍在继续
Fire.
火灾
Unpredictable and destructive.
不可预测且破坏力十足
This is South Africa's fynbos.
这里是南非的弗因博斯
Botanically one of the most diverse habitats on Earth...
是地球上最植物多样化的栖息地之一
..with over 8,000 different plant species.
生长着8000多种不同的植物
Yet, every two decades,
然而 每二十年
fire reduces the vegetation to ashes.
火灾将植被焚烧殆尽
This may seem catastrophic.
这一切看似是毁灭性的
But just days later, plants burst into life...
但就在几天后 植物再次焕发生机
..and transform the landscape.
重塑这片土地
Seeds and bulbs have been waiting for this event.
种子与鳞茎 一直在蛰伏等待这个机会
90 million years of evolution alongside fire
9000万年的进化 使部分植物
has made some plants so closely adapted
得以适应 这片常有火灾的大地
that they can't germinate without the presence of smoke.
以至于种子只有在浓烟下 才会发芽
Remarkably, around 50% of planet Earth's terrestrial habitats
值得注意的是 地球上约50%的陆地栖息地
depend on fire to remain healthy.
依靠火来维持群落健康
In Northern Australia, these savannahs need seasonal fires
在澳大利亚北部 这些稀树草原需要季节性火灾
to keep them open and prevent the spread of the nearby forest.
才能防止森林的扩大 保持草原的开阔
And they are a vital habitat
而对于这一多彩的居民来说
for this colourful resident.
稀树草原是重要的栖息地
The rare golden-shouldered parrot.
稀有的金肩鹦鹉
He and his lifelong partner..
这只雄性鹦鹉 以及它终身的伴侣
rely on grassland for both food...
依赖于草原提供食物
..and a nest site.
以及筑巢地
As usual, they've laid their eggs in a hole in a termite mound.
金肩鹦鹉照例 将卵产在白蚁丘的洞中
And now there are four chicks.
如今育有四只雏鸟
The thick mud walls don't only protect chicks from predators,
厚厚的泥墙 不仅能保护雏鸟免受捕食者伤害
but insulate them from the heat of the scorching sun.
还能遮挡烈日
With fledging just days away,
雏鸟羽翼渐丰
the parents are working overtime.
金肩鹦鹉父母加班加点
They collect thousands of seeds every day.
每天搜集成千上万枚种子
But they have a problem.
然而有一个问题
The fire season is becoming more irregular.
火灾季节变得越来越不规律
If they are not ready to fly,
如果雏鸟还不会飞
chicks have no escape.
它们将无路可逃
But choosing to nest in a termite mound has a surprise benefit.
但选择在白蚁丘中筑巢 有着意想不到的好处
Their home is fireproof.
房子可以防火
Concrete-like walls keep chicks safe from the flames outside.
混泥土般的墙壁 能保护雏鸟不受火焰的伤害
The seeds of fire grass are now easier for the parrots
在烧焦的土地上
to find on the blackened earth...
金肩鹦鹉更容易找到裂稃草的种子
..and they are the parrots' favourite food.
这是它们最爱的食物
So, for both adults and their fledgling chicks...
因此 对于金肩鹦鹉一家来说
..fires are essential for survival.
熊熊烈火对于生存至关重要
But their grassland home is shrinking,
但如今 它们的草原家园正在缩小
and only about 1,000 of these lovely parrots still survive.
只有约1000只可爱的金肩鹦鹉幸存
It's through the active management of fire by humans
通过人类对于火情的积极管理
that their world now exists at all.
金肩鹦鹉的世界才得以存续
Humans are affecting habitats across planet Earth.
人类活动 深刻影响着地球上的栖息地
For wildlife, all too often,
这对于野生动物来说
the consequences have been disastrous.
后果往往是灾难性的
Elephants are among the most tolerant of animals.
大象是耐受力最强的动物之一
They are very long-lived,
它们十分长寿
and knowledge passed between generations enables them
代代相传的知识
to find food and little-used sources of water in times
使大象在极端环境下
of great environmental stress.
能够找到食物和隐蔽的水源
But even among elephants,
但即使如此
survival strategies are now beginning to fail.
大象的生存策略 如今也面临挫折
In Amboseli, Kenya, years of extreme weather,
在肯尼亚的安博塞利 多年的极端天气
combined with overgrazing by domestic cattle,
加上家畜的过度放牧
are turning these grasslands to dust.
使这片草原失去了原有的绿色
This matriarch is over 40 years old...
年逾40岁的首领雌象
..and she's already survived
曾经历过非洲东部
some of East Africa's worst droughts.
最严重的干旱
But this year, food is in extremely short supply...
但今年 食物极度短缺
..and her family are struggling to find enough.
很难满足整个家族的需要
Her youngest son is malnourished and weak...
雌象最小的孩子营养不良 身体虚弱
..and is lagging behind his mother and brother.
落在家族的最后
She leads them to a pocket of acacia forest that she knows well.
雌象带领家族 来到一片熟悉的金合欢树林
But broken branches and fallen trees
然而折断的树枝与倒下的树木
show that other elephants have already been here.
表明其他大象已经来过此处
There is very little left worth eating.
几乎没剩下什么食物
Without food, his mother cannot produce enough milk.
饥肠辘辘的雌象 无法分泌足够的乳汁
She has no choice...
雌象别无选择
..but to leave her weakening calf...
只能留下虚弱的小象
..and try to find food elsewhere.
前往别处寻找食物
So, she and her elder son head off...
因此 小象只能眼睁睁看着母亲与兄长
..without him.
离自己而去
He can only hope for their return.
小象只能寄希望于母亲会回来
But for him, time has run out.
然而时间已经来不及了
There is nothing his mother, or anybody,
面对如此惨剧
could have done to save him.
母亲也无力回天
With her elder son still alive,
大儿子的生命还在继续
there is hope for her family.
大象家族希望尚存
But only if they can adapt quickly.
前提是它们能迅速适应 如此极端的环境
Some families are proving to be resilient.
一些大象家族 展现出了非凡的适应力
They're travelling long distances, away from Amboseli...
它们长途跋涉 离开安博塞利
..and finding new sources of food and water.
寻找新的食物和水源
And despite the drought...
尽管在如此干旱的环境下
..calves are being born.
新生命的诞生从未止步
But given the pace of change
但考虑到环境变化的速度
and the challenges they face...
以及象群面临的严峻挑战
..how many of Africa's elephants will be able to adapt?
究竟有多少非洲大象 能够适应如此极端环境
And can they do so fast enough?
而适应的速度又能来得及吗
The Gobi Desert.
戈壁沙漠
A land of sand and snow.
沙与雪覆盖的大地
For at least a million years, this has been
至少一百万年来 这里一直是
one of the most extreme habitats on Earth.
地球上最极端的栖息地之一
Yet, footprints in the sand
尽管如此 沙子上的足印
reveal that there is life here.
表明这里仍孕育有生命
A snow leopard.
雪豹
Seldom seen...
极其罕见
..especially in such hot, arid conditions.
尤其是在如此炎热干旱的环境下
They live up to 2,000 metres above sea level,
雪豹生存于海拔2000米以上
and patrol vast territories.
掌控广阔的领土
They are rarely seen together.
雪豹极少聚居
A mother...
一只雪豹母亲
..with cubs.
养育着幼崽
Filmed here for the first time
这是首次拍摄到
in such intimate detail.
雪豹如此亲密的画面
And they give us a glimpse of their family life...
这使得我们得以窥见雪豹的家庭生活
..such as it is.
凡此种种
Snow leopard cubs stay with their mothers
雪豹幼崽留在母亲身边的时间
longer than those of almost any other big cat.
几乎比任何大型猫科动物都长
They remain together for over two years...
母子相互陪伴长达两年以上
..as they learn how to master the extremes.
学习在极端环境下的生存之道
Which they do so well that they are able to thrive
使它们得以在地球上最热 最冷
in some of the hottest, coldest...
海拔最高的种种环境下
..and highest places on Earth.
茁壮成长
Some animals, over millions of years,
数百万年的进化 使有些动物
have evolved ways of surviving extremely hostile conditions.
能够在极端恶劣的条件下生存
But as the extremes become more extreme...
但随着环境条件越来越极端
..evolution is being outpaced.
进化渐渐赶不上变化的速度
These extraordinary places are still inhabited
这些非同寻常的地方
by some of Earth's most resilient
仍然居住着一些地球上
and adaptable species.
最具适应力的物种
But in our rapidly changing world...
但在这个瞬息万变的世界
..this is planet Earth as you may never see it again.
如此千姿百态的地球 也许终将成为回不去的过往
幕后花絮
The most extreme parts of our planet
地球上最极端的环境
are not always found where you might expect.
有时位于意想不到的地方
Hidden deep in the forests of Vietnam, a local man,
何康先生隐居于越南的森林深处
Mr Ho Khanh, made an extraordinary discovery.
有一个惊人的发现
One rainy afrernoon
一个下雨的下午
I sheltered in a cave opening.
我躲在一个洞穴里
I saw mist rising from the inside.
我看见洞穴里升起薄雾
It was different from the other caves.
跟别的洞穴不一样
He didn't know it at the time,
尽管当时并不知情
but he had stumbled upon arguably the largest cave in the world.
但他偶然发现了世界上最大的洞穴
to show the world such a magnificent cave
我感到十分荣幸与自豪
It's a source of pride and honour
向世界展示如此一个宏伟的洞穴
Inspired by Mr Ho Khanh's discovery,
从何康的发现中得到启发
the Planet Earth team set out to film Hang Son Doong.
「地球脉动」摄制组动身前往韩松洞进行拍摄
But first, they have to get there.
但首先得能够抵达洞穴
We've left the river valley,
我们离开了河谷
and we're walking uphill now to the entrance.
向上走到入口处
It's just thick, thick forest.
森林特别茂密
After trekking for two gruelling days,
经过两天艰苦的跋涉
the team finally arrive.
摄制组终于抵达了目的地
Down here is the entrance to Hang Son Doong,
下面是韩松洞入口
this tiny opening in this massive jungle.
巨大丛林中的一个小小入口
It's amazing that anyone ever found this place.
能发现这个地方实在是了不起
We're about to go in for the next 18 days,
我们将在里面逗留18天
and it's lights on from here on out.
灯现在开始常亮
Local experts guide the team through the darkness.
当地专家带领摄制组穿过黑暗
OK, I can go?  Yes, yes.
-我可以走吗 -可以了
I'm good. I'm OK.
没问题
It's just really slippery.
洞壁太滑了
A complex system of ropes leads them down a 90-metre descent.
一套复杂的绳索系统 帮助他们向下垂降90米
Watch your head! OK.
-注意别撞到 -好的
Thanks.
谢谢
After four hours clambering over rocks...
在岩石上攀爬了四个小时后
...they finally reach what will be their camp.
他们终于抵达了营地
The team wake to a new day -
迎来新的一天
but in darkness.
但四下黑漆漆一片
How did you sleep, Luke?
睡得怎么样 卢克
Quite tired.
还是很累
These are all of the tents behind me.
这些都是我身后的帐篷
You can see they are pretty...
可以看到这些帐篷
..pretty snug.
都挺舒适
This is where we have our breakfast every day,
这是我们每天吃早餐的地方
made by some amazing cooks.
厨师手艺精湛
This is our charging station.
这里是充电站
Batteries for camera equipment, batteries for our lights,
相机的电池 灯的电池
our head torches, which are so important.
头戴式电筒的电池 至关重要
This is our water station.
这里是供水站
Everything that we have got has been brought in by someone,
所有东西都是别人千辛万苦搬进来的
so you can't shower or wash.
所以不能洗澡洗衣服
And it's not just water.
除了水以外
Tonnes of equipment has had to be carried into the cave,
还要将成吨的设备搬进洞内
every inch of the way.
一步一个脚印
Now deep underground, the powerful lights
现在在地底深处
reveal just how vast this cavern is.
光照显示出这个洞穴究竟有多大
That is amazing.
太不可思议了
Look at that. It's...
看哪 这里简直
It's huge!
简直太大了
As you turn on each of the lights,
随着一盏盏灯被点亮
another part of this enormous chamber is revealed.
洞穴深处的黑暗被驱散
It's magic. Absolutely magic.
太神奇了
To try and capture the true scale,
为了展现真实的尺度
the team attempt a filming technique never tried before.
摄制组尝试了一种新的拍摄技术
We're trying to do a little bit of a dance with the drones,
我们正尝试让无人机起舞
whereby we have one drone sort of slightly below the other,
一台无人机略低于另一台
one filming the other one lighting a feature in the cave.
一台负责照明 一台负责拍摄
It's a really tight space.
空间特别狭小
You can't see anything.
伸手不见五指
What could go wrong?
情况不能再糟了
OK, slow down a bit.
慢一点
It's making everyone a little nervous.
每个人都有些紧张
Yeah, don't go up any higher, Luke.
不能再高了 卢克
OK, that's a nice height.
这个高度不错
With one drone lighting and one drone filming...
一台无人机照明 一台拍摄
..they reveal the wonder of some of the world's largest stalagmites.
为我们展现了 一些世界上最大的奇特石笋
As the days pass, the team settle into
随着时间流逝 摄制组适应了
the everyday routine of life underground.
地底的日常工作
This is the epitome of being off-grid.
这是脱离尘世的写照
We call that one seesaw loo
我们叫它跷跷板厕所
because it's kind of on a rock,
因为它下面有颗石头
and every time you sit on it and lean back,
每次坐在上面都会后倾
you're scared that there's going to be a disaster.
不禁让人担心会弄得一团糟
The strangest thing is having no connection
最异样的是我们跟外界
to the outside world whatsoever.
没有任何联系
Time is warped. Nothing makes sense underground.
生物钟彻底紊乱 地底下一切都不一样了
Lights on!
开灯
Without daylight to guide them, the team work round the clock
没有日光的指引 摄制组不分昼夜地工作
to capture the cave's most unique features.
拍摄洞穴中独特的镜头
Most special of all,
最特别的是
an event which happens only a few weeks a year.
一年中只持续几周的活动
To get there, they must navigate
为了到达那里 他们必须穿过
through boulder fields and tight squeezes.
巨石区和狭窄的道路
Here, around half a million years ago,
在这里 约50万年前
the cave roof collapsed,
洞顶坍塌下来
opening a window to the outside world.
开启了一扇通往外界的窗
The team wait for just the right conditions.
摄制组等待合适的条件
We've been sat here for hours.
我们坐在这几小时了
And finally, just on the right-hand side of the wall,
最后 在右侧的墙上
we can see the first signs of light.
能找到光线的踪迹
After weeks of darkness
经过数周的黑暗
200 metres underground...
在200米深的地底
..they see sunlight
他们看到阳光
illuminate the cave floor.
照亮了洞穴
The way it just lights up this massive cave...
整个巨大洞穴都被照亮了
..when we've been trying to do it with about four or five lights
我们本来试图用四五盏灯点亮这里
and barely even lighting the smallest section.
结果根本行不通
When the sun comes in, it just...
阳光照进来的时候
I think everyone's got goose bumps.
我相信每个人都起鸡皮疙瘩了
I don't think I've ever appreciated sun so much in my life.
我想这是我第一次如此感激太阳
It's incredible.
太难以置信了
Look at the backlit waterfalls.
看那些背光的瀑布
They're so slow coming down.
坠落如此缓慢
It's literally one of the best things I've ever seen.
这真是我见过最美好的事情之一
For the crew, the sunbeam marks a profound end
对于摄制组来说 阳光标志着
to their time in the cave.
洞穴作业画上句号
We're outside!
我们出来了
It's so green, it's so bright.
绿色的丛林 明媚的阳光
Being back above ground feels like where we belong.
回到地面上 满满的归属感
It's a wonder to imagine what other extremes
地球表面之下究竟还隐藏着
still lie beneath the surface of planet Earth.
什么样的极端环境 实在是不可思议
Next time...
下一集
..the human world...
人类世界
..where animals must find new ways to survive...
在这里 动物必须探索新的方式
..amongst us.
与我们共存
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
「栖息地探索者」生动地展现动物和它们的栖息地
Explore this free interactive, and make origami animals.
探索这个免费互动程序并制作折纸动物
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
前往bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
and follow the links to the Open University.
点击链接进入开放大学
Or to order a free printed version, visit the website
或者订购免费印刷版
or call the numbers on the screen.
欢迎访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码